<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections on the city-charter and writ of quo warranto together with a vindication of the late sheriffs and juries.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58359</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11058126</idno>
  <idno type="VID">46186</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240943188</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R704</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29261</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11058126</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58359)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1429:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections on the city-charter and writ of quo warranto together with a vindication of the late sheriffs and juries.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E. Smith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through and cropped pages, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">London (England) --  Charters, grants, privileges.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">London (England) --  Politics and government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46186:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46186:1"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS ON THE City-Charter, AND WRIT OF Quo Warranto.</p>
            <p>Together with a VINDICATION Of the late SHERIFFS and JURIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imperia Legum potentiora quam Hominum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>E. Smith</hi> at the <hi>Elephant</hi> and <hi>Castle</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> MDCLXXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46186:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46186:2"/>
            <head>REFLECTIONS ON THE <hi>City-Charter, ❧c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is very obvious to any indifferent <hi>Observer,</hi> that the weekly Pamphlets of our <hi>Popish,</hi> or <hi>Popishly affected Scriblers,</hi> and the spiteful Herangues of many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerate or designing <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> with the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of some <hi>Degenerate Citizens</hi> have possessed divers well-meaning Persons with great prejudices, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished them with variety of <hi>Objections</hi> against the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Constitutions</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of this CITY, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly quarrelling at the <hi>Conduct</hi> of our late <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and <hi>Jurors,</hi> who are according to the Information and Advices, we daily receive from these <hi>Impudent Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> entred into a Confederacy to affront the <hi>King,</hi> sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>Laws,</hi> obstruct the equal <hi>Administration</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice</hi> between our <hi>Sovereign</hi> and his <hi>Liege Subjects,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing those, who are well affected to his <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> countenancing and acquitting the <hi>disaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted</hi> and <hi>turbulent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That any whose Habitation is remote from this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who are unacquainted with its <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> comprehended in a <hi>Famous Charter (Superior</hi> to all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting the great <hi>National One</hi> so dearly purchased, so highly valued by all <hi>Englishmen,</hi> who have not extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>degenerated</hi> from the <hi>Honesty</hi> and <hi>Courage</hi> of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Progenitors</hi>) That such Strangers, I say, to us and our Affairs should through <hi>Ignorance</hi> or <hi>Misinformation</hi> censure and condemn our late <hi>Transactions</hi> is no <hi>Subject</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:46186:3"/> of <hi>Admiration;</hi> as neither that the <hi>Hireling</hi> half famish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Patrons of the so often <hi>bafled Popish Cause</hi> should give such odious <hi>Characters</hi> of us: But we cannot resist being affected with <hi>grief</hi> and <hi>indignation,</hi> that an <hi>Unnatural Brood</hi> hatch'd in this our CITY, who have thence derived all the <hi>Advantages</hi> of a quiet easie life, many the <hi>Comfort</hi> and <hi>Conveniences</hi> of a plentiful <hi>Estate,</hi> and some of them loaded with <hi>Honour,</hi> should yet most ingratefully expose the Mother, who did both bear and educate them unto undeserved <hi>Contumely</hi> for the present, and, I may add, to manifest ruin for the future, should <hi>Events</hi> (which God forbid) depend upon their unhallowed <hi>Wishes</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied <hi>Endeavours.</hi> I have not set <hi>Pen</hi> to <hi>Paper</hi> in order to the <hi>Instructing</hi> or in hopes of <hi>Converting</hi> those re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved desperate Persons, who design and have vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Subversion</hi> of our <hi>Antient, Laudable, Constitutions;</hi> Nor do I write principally for the sake of those weak, ductile persons, who are influenced and actuated by an implicite Faith, suffer themselves to be managed by cunning <hi>Gamesters,</hi> and by them wheedled into a persua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, that by parting with their fair, <hi>present Possessions,</hi> they shall obtain far better in <hi>reversion,</hi> yet offering no <hi>Security</hi> in the <hi>interim</hi> to make good their <hi>Undertaking,</hi> besides a bare <hi>Parole,</hi> which hath been already many times violated or forfeited. The Errors of such Persons are next step to incureable, they usually not consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is said, but by whom; and if contrary to the <hi>Sentiments</hi> and <hi>Lectures</hi> of their <hi>Leaders,</hi> or contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory to their mistaken corrupt <hi>Interests,</hi> with great <hi>clamour</hi> they decry the most visible <hi>Truths,</hi> the most co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>Arguments</hi> for <hi>Falshood</hi> and <hi>Impertinency:</hi> But I write for the <hi>Information</hi> of <hi>divers Persons,</hi> who tho under mistakes, are yet <hi>honest</hi> and <hi>sincere, indiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rent</hi> what is <hi>Truth, dilligent Inquirers</hi> after it; and being enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby, do accommodate their <hi>words</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> unto its <hi>Dictates.</hi> Such <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Citizens,</hi> I design
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46186:3"/> chiefly to serve, and for <hi>their sakes</hi> have employed some leisure hours in making a true and faithful <hi>Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the <hi>Present State</hi> of our <hi>City,</hi> and of the behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our of those <hi>Magistrates</hi> in whom of recent memory, the <hi>Citizens</hi> have reposed the greatest <hi>Trust,</hi> I mean <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs,</hi> and <hi>Juries</hi> by them appointed; upon whose dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and Integrity, all that is dear unto us depends, our <hi>Lives, Liberties, Estates,</hi> would to God there were no need to add, and in some respects our <hi>Religion</hi> also. I do not in the least doubt, before I put a <hi>Period</hi> to this <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course</hi> fully to convince all, who are unprejudiced and <hi>considerate,</hi> that those very persons, who have long been, and still are, the <hi>Song</hi> of the <hi>Drunkard,</hi> the Subject of a Thousand Railleries and Reproaches in all <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Entertainments</hi> of <hi>True Papists,</hi> and false, or mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided, seduced <hi>Protestants,</hi> do yet really deserve the warm Affections and high Esteem of all <hi>Honest English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Good Protestants,</hi> and <hi>Discreetely Loyal Subjests.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I proceed to their Vindication, it will not be amiss to premise by whom so many scandalous, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitious <hi>Reports</hi> have been raised, by whom so many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just groundless aspersions have been contrived, foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, propogated. After diligent enquiry, long obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and frequent converse with Persons of divers perswasions and qualities; I have arrived unto a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in my own mind, that manifest declared <hi>Papists</hi> and others, not professedly such, but in reality friends unto and Correspondents with that Party, are the Persons who observe, aggravate, and spread all these Stories and opinions that are likely to weaken the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Interest,</hi> create misunderstandings between <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> of different apprehensions, thereby to embroil and if possible breed irreconcilable divisions and feuds amongst them; having thus sowed the seeds of Distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and consequently of Destruction amongst us, how sedulously did they cultivate the weed, which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46186:4"/> had they patience, in time might have effected their purpose, but the sprightly enterprizing <hi>Emissaries</hi> of the <hi>Roman Communion</hi> finding their designes not ripen according to their expectation, have recourse to their own peculiar tried Acts of Lying <hi>Perjury</hi> and <hi>Suborna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> hopeing by these means to Extricate themselves out of the <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of their so often proved, so clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonstrated, and fully detected Conspiracy, and to cast the <hi>Odium</hi> of their detestable principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices on such of the Innocent <hi>Protestants</hi> as were most zealous for their own Religion, or active against theirs, whose courage, Quality, Estates, or interest made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear formidable Adversaries, and likely to obstruct a hopeful design, which had been long hatching, was once neer the Birth, but by a train of <hi>Providences,</hi> miraculously discovered, and for them unhappily dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed. It were a difficult task to trace them through all their crooked <hi>Paths:</hi> no small labour to bring to light all their misterious hidden works of <hi>Darkness.</hi> Let us be content with our Ignorance of some few of their hellish <hi>Machinations,</hi> enough appearing to all whoare not voluntarily blind: and sufficient to render the <hi>Contrivers</hi> and <hi>Actors</hi> abominable, and as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst whom they were designed; thankful that we have been hitherto delivered from the effects of their <hi>Malice and Cruelty:</hi> It is high time to be jealous of them, we cannot be too watchful and Circumspect af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter so many narrow escapes, which to recall unto your <hi>Memories</hi> would be a great piece of <hi>Impertinency,</hi> did not daily <hi>Experience</hi> manifest a sort of <hi>pretended Protestants</hi> who make it almost their <hi>sole Imployment</hi> to palliate, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate, and if possibly, to obliterate out of our minds the remembrance of so formidable a <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> a <hi>Plot</hi> owned and stigmatized by <hi>His Majesty</hi> in divers <hi>Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> and by <hi>Four Successive Parliaments:</hi> The <hi>First</hi> of which was so far from being composed of <hi>Dissenters,</hi> that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46186:4"/> they alone forged the <hi>Fetters</hi> with which the <hi>Protestant Dissenters</hi> are now manacled. How many of the <hi>Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators</hi> were upon fair <hi>Tryals</hi> and full <hi>Evidence convict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> and <hi>executed: Colemans</hi> own <hi>Letters,</hi> being <hi>Witnesses,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst which no <hi>Rational Objection</hi> was ever yet raised. Let us not forget how <hi>providentially Dangerfield</hi>'s <hi>Plot</hi> was defeated, whereby the <hi>Packet</hi> of <hi>Letters</hi> to have been <hi>Concealed,</hi> and after by the <hi>hider</hi> discovered, was to have <hi>Accused</hi> many Worthy <hi>Nobles</hi> and <hi>Gentlemen:</hi> soon after others were to have been conveyed to divers <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Citizens</hi> of the best Account throughout the <hi>Nation;</hi> but being <hi>Intercepted</hi> in <hi>Celiers Meal Tub,</hi> the hopeful <hi>Project</hi> proved <hi>Abortive.</hi> But so many <hi>Disappointments</hi> did not excite <hi>Desperation</hi> in the <hi>magnanimous Romanists,</hi> who, tho so often routed, rallied their <hi>Forces,</hi> had recours to new <hi>Strategems,</hi> but still stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on the old <hi>String,</hi> to entangle the <hi>Innocent Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> and render them obnoxious to the utmost severity of the <hi>Law;</hi> destroy their <hi>Bodies,</hi> confiscate their <hi>Estates,</hi> murder their <hi>Reputation,</hi> and reproach their <hi>Religion.</hi> All these would have certainly ensued had any of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Sham-Plots</hi> succeeded, or what immediately followed, the <hi>Contrivance</hi> of <hi>Fitz-Harris,</hi> who undertook to frame a <hi>Venemous Libel,</hi> full fraught with <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Treason;</hi> this was by apt <hi>Instruments</hi> to have bin convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the <hi>Houses</hi> and <hi>Pockets</hi> of divers Eminent <hi>Persons</hi> devoted to <hi>Destruction,</hi> and they thereupon proceeded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst as the worst of <hi>Traitors.</hi> But all these mischie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous <hi>Contrivances</hi> falling on their own <hi>Pates,</hi> a new <hi>Scene</hi> appears: They having imployed in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> many Persons of <hi>mean Fortunes, bad Principles,</hi> and <hi>worse Lives</hi> to carry on their <hi>Conspiracy;</hi> some of their <hi>Agents,</hi> having upon the <hi>publick Faith</hi> Assurance of <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity,</hi> and <hi>Promise of Reward</hi> greater than they could reasonably expect from their <hi>Principals</hi> came in for <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses</hi> against them, but having <hi>slender Countenance,</hi> very
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46186:5"/>
               <hi>mean Allowance</hi> and no <hi>Prospect</hi> of <hi>Reward,</hi> the <hi>Protestants</hi> fearful to maintain them, least they should seem there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to <hi>dishonour</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and influence the <hi>Evidence</hi> to accommodate their <hi>Testimonies</hi> unto the desires of those <hi>Gentlemen</hi> and <hi>Citizens,</hi> by whom they should be suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and relieved. The <hi>Romanists</hi> quickly espy this <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</hi> and immediately by large <hi>Promises</hi> and some considerable <hi>Performances</hi> gain them to <hi>Retract</hi> their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence against <hi>Themselves,</hi> and <hi>accuse</hi> those <hi>Protestants,</hi> with whom they had frequent, intimate <hi>Converse;</hi> and some others into whose <hi>Presence</hi> they had scarcely ever been <hi>admitted.</hi> Hereby they did infallibly assure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of these <hi>Advantages,</hi> if they were <hi>Believed,</hi> to take off their <hi>Enemies;</hi> if <hi>Credit</hi> was not given unto them, the <hi>Former Testimony</hi> they gave against the <hi>Conspirators</hi> would be rendred <hi>invalid.</hi> And besides they gained this further <hi>Improvement</hi> of their <hi>Evidence</hi> being reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted (upon grounds we shall hereafter mention) that hereby they raised a great <hi>Outcry</hi> of the <hi>Partiallity</hi> of <hi>JURIES,</hi> who would <hi>believe</hi> the same <hi>Witnesses</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Papists,</hi> and reject when they <hi>Accused Protestants</hi> of the same <hi>Crimes;</hi> and having cunningly hounded their <hi>Proselyted Witnesses</hi> on <hi>PERSONS</hi> not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to a great body of <hi>PROTESTANTS</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us, upon whose acquittal, with the help of their spightful <hi>Insinuations,</hi> a great clamour was made, the King could have no <hi>Justice,</hi> this Affair <hi>Misrepresented</hi> by our Enemies, is the Original, and Sourse of all our <hi>Calamities,</hi> our <hi>City, Sheriffs</hi> and <hi>Juries</hi> being thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rendred suspected, a <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> issued out against the <hi>Charter;</hi> The <hi>Sheriffs</hi> threatned, afrighted, and upon every slender occasion hampered: New and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of <hi>Acts</hi> to obtain a <hi>Sheriff;</hi> probably designed for some extraordinary service. The Common <hi>Citizens</hi> affrighted and perplexed, lest they should be deprived of their ancient <hi>Customs</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> upon the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46186:5"/> whereof their <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> depends: and who can doubt but all these <hi>Disorders</hi> and <hi>Misprisions</hi> are the result of the <hi>Papists</hi> concerning the King, <hi>Exaspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating</hi> both his Majesty and the Judges against the <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs</hi> and <hi>Juries,</hi> who were they, to judg by number and not by weight, would appear utterly unexcusable, but hereof anon at large: Howsoever from this indisputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter of <hi>Fact</hi> which we have related, it appears that the <hi>Papists</hi> incessantly <hi>Plot</hi> to destroy the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants,</hi> which not being able to effect by force, they have narrowly escaped, effecting it more then once by <hi>Subornation</hi> and <hi>Perjury.</hi> Therefore it behooves all <hi>Protestants</hi> to be extreamly circumspect, prepare for and provide against all those mischiefs they have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to expect from a subtle Potent <hi>Enemy:</hi> And there can no more appropriate and effectual <hi>Antitode</hi> be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed or even desired against this <hi>Itallian</hi> poyson of <hi>Perjury,</hi> than judicious honest <hi>Juries:</hi> Which of all Societies, Cities, Persons, that of <hi>London</hi> and its <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants</hi> ought to secure, they being more exposed to the danger of <hi>Popish</hi> malice and cruelty, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part of the <hi>English Nation.</hi> For though the hatred of the <hi>Romanists</hi> extends it self to the whole body of <hi>Protestants,</hi> yet their animosity manifests it self, and their <hi>Attempts</hi> are chiefly levelled against this <hi>City,</hi> they accounting it as really it is the great <hi>Bulwark</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> which being battered down by open force, or secretly undermined, a breach would be opened through, which <hi>Popery</hi> would flow like a torrent with its inseperable attendants <hi>Ignorance, Cruelty,</hi> and <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> whether they have any ways contributed to the debating and impoverishing this City, will readily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to those who believe that the burning of the City was contrived, begun and carryed on by them, none can doubt who have heard of <hi>Huberts</hi> Confession, or read the <hi>Depositions</hi> made before the darling long <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:46186:6"/> the Evidence then given being so clear, both from the number and quality of the <hi>Witnesses,</hi> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriety of the <hi>Fact,</hi> as constrained that numerous <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee</hi> to conclude <hi>Papists</hi> were the principle, if not its only incendiaries: And latter Evidence hath discover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed they did not only destroy our Habitations, but rob and make spoil of our goods, as if we had been Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of War, and they had taken our City by <hi>Storm.</hi> And we are abundantly confirmed in this belief, by the Authority of that great Integruous <hi>Minister</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Lord <hi>Chancellor,</hi> who in the most <hi>August, Illustrious Assembly</hi> this Age hath known, himself in the <hi>highest place of Honour</hi> hath been since his <hi>Majesty</hi>'s Raign con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on any <hi>Subject;</hi> upon the <hi>Tryal</hi> of a great <hi>Popish Peer,</hi> did most <hi>solemnly</hi> and <hi>positively</hi> charge <hi>Papists</hi> with that <hi>detestable Hellish Fact,</hi> which gave occasion of that <hi>Inscription</hi> in our <hi>Mother-Tongue</hi> on that stupendious <hi>Pillar,</hi> erected to be a <hi>Lasting Monument</hi> of <hi>Gods Justice</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> to us wards, and of <hi>perpetual Ignominy,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that <hi>Restless Faction,</hi> who to <hi>consummate</hi> their <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> would certainly, were it in their power, mix our <hi>Bloud</hi> with our <hi>Sacrifices,</hi> and our <hi>CITY</hi> with <hi>Salt.</hi> Such have been their <hi>Actions,</hi> now to manifest what <hi>Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> they entertain either of <hi>Fear</hi> or <hi>Revenge,</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to this <hi>Abhorred City,</hi> I shall out of many <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts,</hi> I have received from <hi>Credible Witnesses</hi> select only <hi>Two,</hi> which I received immediately from <hi>Persons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent</hi> during the ensuing <hi>Discourses;</hi> The <hi>First</hi> of a <hi>noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Papist</hi> eminent both for <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Quality,</hi> who fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly and frankly <hi>communicating</hi> to <hi>divers Gentlemen,</hi> whom he apprehended to be <hi>All</hi> of his <hi>own Religion,</hi> rendring an <hi>Account</hi> of the hopeful <hi>Posture</hi> of their <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,</hi> after much <hi>boasting,</hi> he assured them, <hi>They were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensive of no danger from any Quarter, except that damn'd Rebellious, Fanatical</hi> CITY <hi>of</hi> LONDON, <hi>which might chance in Three Days to turn the Tide, disappoint and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46186:6"/> their most hopeful Projections:</hi> The <hi>Other</hi> was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable <hi>Herangue</hi> made by a <hi>Mascarade Protestant,</hi> a <hi>Militia man,</hi> and pretendedly <hi>zealous Defender</hi> of our <hi>Faith</hi> in the <hi>Company</hi> of at least <hi>Five Auditors,</hi> after se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Souldier-like Rants</hi> and bitter <hi>Invectives</hi> against the CITY, he at length thus <hi>Pathetically</hi> concluded, <hi>The</hi> CITY <hi>of</hi> London <hi>never hitherto yielded me a pleasant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect, saving once, when in flames, and I hope shortly to enjoy the Satisfaction of Seeing it in the same Condition, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can render this Nation Happy.</hi> Do not question, but these are the <hi>Sentiments</hi> of most <hi>Papists</hi> and their <hi>Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents,</hi> but they generally express themselves more wari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet no less <hi>maliciously,</hi> the former base <hi>Dialect</hi> would be too gross, might chance to <hi>awaken</hi> an <hi>Alarmn</hi> some not over dangerous <hi>Protestants,</hi> who are immerst in a <hi>profound Lethargick sleep,</hi> and will, I fear, never awake, to <hi>see</hi> their danger, till they <hi>feel</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Amongst such as these, they are continually sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting the <hi>Temper</hi> and <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the <hi>City,</hi> during the last <hi>unnatural Civil War,</hi> as if the present <hi>Citizens</hi> were to reckon for all the <hi>Bloodshed</hi> and <hi>Confusion</hi> during the late <hi>Troubles.</hi> And that if the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of the <hi>Supream Magistrate</hi> do not prevent, the same Cause will Revive, the old <hi>Quarrel</hi> will be fought over again, the same <hi>Spirit</hi> inspiring, the same <hi>Principles</hi> acting, and <hi>ferment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the Generality of <hi>Citizens</hi> which prevailed in 41. that 'tis necessary such ill disaffected Persons should have no share in the <hi>Government,</hi> which would afford them opportunity of perpetrating all imaginable Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs. Let us now examine what <hi>Foundation</hi> there is for such <hi>Insinuations:</hi> I do not question but the CITY of <hi>London,</hi> as at this present time, is well-affected to his <hi>Majesties Person,</hi> as it hath ever been to any preceding <hi>Prince,</hi> I am no less certain, that very <hi>Party</hi> upon whom our <hi>Objectors</hi> squint do more stedily and sincerely desire
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46186:7"/> his <hi>Majesties</hi> Life and Welfare than they who oppose and expose them, and I find that our <hi>Citizens</hi> have gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally (especially those we now vindicate) a most huge value for the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Established Government</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> and in this respect so far from being <hi>Men given to Change,</hi> that there is nothing in the <hi>World</hi> whereof they are more Apprehensive; Most of those, with whom I am conversant, (assured me) would <hi>joyfully</hi> part with a great <hi>Portion</hi> of their <hi>Estates</hi> to be secured of that <hi>Legal Administration,</hi> which we have (blessed be God) enjoyed ever since his <hi>Majesties Glorious</hi> Restauration. But, besides, the Calamities and Miseries of the late <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Wars</hi> are so lively imprinted in all considerate <hi>minds</hi> and have rendred them so averse to imitate the <hi>Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors</hi> herein, that I find them generally inclined to suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to a very <hi>High Degree,</hi> before they would so much as consult, how they might preserve what all <hi>Laws</hi> of God and Men allow to be maintained, and defend if <hi>unjustly</hi> invaded. Who then are these <hi>Factious, Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Rebellious, Traiterous, dangerous, Citizens,</hi> whom we ought to hate, expose, avoid, disarm, outlaw and punish when you desire a <hi>Description</hi> of them, a <hi>Catalogue</hi> that you might know them, and avoid the <hi>Malignity</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion</hi> of their <hi>Company</hi> and <hi>Converse,</hi> get out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst, that you escape being destroyed with them? You shall have for Answer, <hi>They are Phanaticks, Men of Commonwealth Principles, Parliamentarians,</hi> but if you press them to a more particular Definition of these <hi>Furies</hi> in their less <hi>Reserved Mode,</hi> or if you happen to hear them <hi>Rant</hi> it among their <hi>Comarades,</hi> unconceivable,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are such as do not <hi>desire, pray,</hi> or <hi>address</hi> for a <hi>Blessing</hi> of a <hi>Popish Successor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. All who do not <hi>Abhor</hi> the <hi>Proceedings</hi> of the Three last <hi>Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. All who do not <hi>Abhor</hi> all <hi>Associations</hi> for preserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our <hi>Liberties</hi> and the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46186:7"/> that <hi>pretended</hi> to be found in the E. of S. Closet.</p>
            <p n="4">4. All who talk of <hi>Parliaments</hi> for the future, and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if any think it adviseable, with all duty and profoundest humility, to bring to His <hi>Majesty</hi>'s Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the <hi>Constitution</hi> of our <hi>Government,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires <hi>Frequent Parliaments,</hi> and His <hi>Majesties Gracious Promise, That He would frequently oblige his People there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Such as in the <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> hope and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there are any <hi>Honest, Loyal, Protestant Dissenters,</hi> and especially, if they have any <hi>Regard</hi> to those <hi>Votes</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> which declared such <hi>Dissenters, Fit Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of his Majesties Clemency,</hi> who desire the <hi>Relaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of some, and <hi>Abolishing</hi> other <hi>Statutes</hi> made against them, and <hi>dehort</hi> all Persons from Subjecting them meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon a <hi>Religious Account</hi> to the <hi>Severity</hi> of <hi>Penal Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. All who will rake the <hi>Popish Plot</hi> out of its <hi>Ashes,</hi> who will not allow the <hi>Papists</hi> to be a part of His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties</hi> best Subjects, from whom in those Mens Opinion there is little or no danger, but certainly abundantly less than from the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Commonwealths</hi> men, and <hi>Favour</hi> is at this Time especially to be shewed, whereby we may <hi>Moderate</hi> the <hi>Persecution</hi> against the <hi>Poor Protestants</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> that there is no <hi>Sort</hi> or <hi>Rank</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> who have more <hi>Candour</hi> and <hi>Goodness</hi> in their <hi>Nature, Civility</hi> in their <hi>Demeanour,</hi> none more for <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> or more against <hi>Parliamentarian Democrasy</hi> and <hi>Tyranny:</hi> Their <hi>Principles</hi> with some small Allowance and favourable Construction, easily <hi>Reconcileable</hi> to the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> their <hi>Officers, Garments, Ceremonies</hi> to the <hi>Discipline</hi> of the <hi>English Hierarchy:</hi> That the <hi>Fanaticks</hi> is a <hi>Common Enemy</hi> to both, therefore having an <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Interest;</hi> there should be one of <hi>Hearts,</hi> a <hi>Combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> to suppress the <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> and then after at leisure in a calm, friendly way to compose and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate their small differences.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:46186:8"/>7. Another sort of Pestilent fellows are those who hinder the Disturbers of the Nation from being brought to condign punishment, such have been all our <hi>Modern SHERIFFS,</hi> and most part of our <hi>JU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RIES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. They who are unwilling their <hi>CHARTER</hi> should be taken away, and who do <hi>Defend</hi> the <hi>Legal Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges</hi> and <hi>Antient Customs</hi> of this Renowned CITY of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Five</hi> Parts in <hi>Six</hi> of this great CITY coming under some, and the Majority under all those <hi>Reproofs</hi> you may readily imagine, that with those Censors, our CITY is very <hi>whiggish, malignant, Anti-monarchical.</hi> We are mostly a <hi>Tiptoe,</hi> need only a pretence, a Head, and the blowing of a <hi>Trumpet</hi> to put us in uproar.</p>
            <p>The <hi>First</hi> will be to <hi>massacre</hi> the <hi>Papists, the poor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Papists,</hi> and his <hi>Loyal, Magnanimous younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tory Tom,</hi> the two great <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next comes in the <hi>Old Prank</hi> of <hi>Rifling Princes,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Tinder</hi> of <hi>Lawn Sleeves,</hi> then break upon us <hi>Swarms</hi> of <hi>Sects,</hi> innumerable as <hi>Insects,</hi> and that <hi>Hohgob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Leviathan</hi> in <hi>Civil Government</hi> stalks over <hi>Crowned Heads, Princes</hi> and <hi>Nobles,</hi> trampling under foot all <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Equity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What I have repeated is not the Thousand <hi>Part</hi> of what is commonly <hi>Herangued</hi> by our <hi>Abhorrers</hi> of a <hi>Protestant Successor,</hi> and a <hi>Monarchy</hi> confined within the <hi>Narrow Limits,</hi> which <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Reason</hi> have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed, we shall examine the <hi>Maximes</hi> of these, at the same time, querelous and insolent <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> confute
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46186:8"/> their frivolous <hi>Pretentions</hi> to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reason;</hi> and <hi>lastly,</hi> vindicate our <hi>Loyal, Integruous, coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Magistrates,</hi> our <hi>Intelligent, upright, unby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>assed, JURORS;</hi> our Honest and peaceable <hi>Fellow-Citizens,</hi> from the Calumnies of Men, whose Design and Business is to create pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Disturbances.</p>
            <p>We shall expose and unravel those perverse Reasonings, and Sophisticate Arguments, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they endeavour to obscure and perplex Truth, the Light whereof will shine through the Mist and Dust they have raised to Ecclipse her.</p>
            <p>Most of the forementioned objections have been so frequently and strenuously refuted that it is amazing any should have forehead enough to repeat them. Their zeal for a Popish Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sour, is for reasons best known to themselves at present Dorment. And a late Tryal, together with some expressions which the notoriety of the Fact, and irresistible power of Truth, extorted from our great Justiciary, hath somwhat dampt and checkt their hopes of stiffling the Popish Plot, that which they urge at present with most vigour is the abandoning of our Charter, a resigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof is necessary by reason of our unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46186:9"/> abuse, of so gracious concessions, by choosing Sheriffs who return Juries, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all humane and divine Laws, condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Innocent, and acquitting the Guilty, both alike abominable before God and Man.</p>
            <p>It will be necessary in order to the more clear and distinct resolution of these Objections to give a summary account of the Nature and most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Contents of our City Charter, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with some obvious suitable Reflections there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then we appeal to all endued with Reason, who have any observation upon the vastly dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent effect of good and bad or no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whether this City hath cause voluntarily to resign that which above all other means hath most contributed to its Grandieur and security: and herein we may safely imitate <hi>Diogenes,</hi> whose generous freedom was commended by the great <hi>Alexander</hi> himself, which mighty Monarch inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing between him and the Sun: Stand aside said he, and deprive me not of that which thou canst not impart unto me, meaning the benign influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of its Light and Heat. But to make good our promise of representing under one view, the sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of our invaluable Charter, which is of so great Antiquity, that I know not from what time to reckon its date, for this City being by its
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46186:9"/> Situation rarely qualified to become the Scale of Trade, and Seat of Empire, hath enjoyed the former without Interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, above 1600 Years, as appears from <hi>Tacitus,</hi> an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of unquestioned Authority: and the latter, almost e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver since the Heptarchy was reduced under one Monarch; The Saxon and afterwards, the Norman Race having always given it the Preference, honouring it with their Residence, fixing here their Courts of Judicature, and endowing it successively with greater Priviledges than were ever enjoyed by any City in the Universe, old <hi>Rome</hi> it self not being except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Our Records are silent what their Priviledges were, during the Dominion of the Saxons; but since they were certainly very considerable, they so valiantly in Fight maintaining them, and, after the Loss of their Prince, made Terms with the Norman, their Weapons in their Hands, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to be their King, upon Condition, he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm unto them the Laws of good King <hi>Edward,</hi> which was graunted in these Terms: <hi>I give you to understand, I will that you enjoy all the Laws, you enjoyed in the Days of King</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>and I will not suffer that any Man to do you wrong.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of these Laws are specified with Additions in the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, granted by <hi>Henry</hi> Son to <hi>Willam the Norman,</hi> which is published with his Laws a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> large by <hi>Wheelock, p.</hi> 176. which begins thus: <hi>Sciatis me concessisse Civibus meis London. tenend. Middlesex ad firmam pro CCC libr' ad Compotum ipsius &amp; haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus suis de me &amp; haeredibus meis; ita ut ipsi Cives ponent Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. qualem voluerint de seipsis, &amp; Ius<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ar. qualem voluerint de seipsis,</hi> &amp;c. He granted the Citizens to chuse out of them selves a Sheriff for the County of <hi>Middlesex,</hi> and a Justice for Pleas of the Crown. King <hi>John</hi> confirmed unto them in his second Charter the Sheriffwick of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex,</hi> with all Customes and Emoluments thereto appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And further graunted, that the Citizens among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves might make Sheriffs whom they would, and remove them whensoever they pleased: and the said Sheriffs, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46186:10"/> their Office, not to be condemned to any Amerciament or Mulct of Money, exceeding 20 li. These were all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed with Additions by his Son <hi>Henry the Third;</hi> who in another Charter concedes unto his Barons of the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> that they may annually chuse out of themselves a Mayor for the Government of the City, and at the end of the Year to confirm or remove him, and substitute another at their Pleasure. It is by many controverted, who those Barons were, who are in this and other Charters mentioned, out of whom the Mayor was to be chosen; Whether all Freemen, or Persons of the greatest Quality and Authority in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: <hi>Matthew Paris pag.</hi> 893. <hi>Cives Londinenses quos propter Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis dignitatem &amp; Civium antiquam Libertatem Barones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suevimus appellare.</hi> And <hi>pag.</hi> 974. <hi>Convocaverunt in Aula</hi> Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall <hi>appellata totius Civitatis Cives, quos Barones vocant.</hi> This was during the Reign of <hi>Henry the third.</hi> But long before I find in <hi>Malmesbury, pag.</hi> 189. concerning the Imprison<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King <hi>Stephen: Barones Londinenses, qui sunt quasi Optimates, pro magnitudine Civitatis in Anglia.</hi> To the said Barons in the same Charter was graunted and confirmed, that they might have in Peace, freely, quietly, entirely all their Liberty ever before used in <hi>London</hi> or without, by Land or Water, and all other Places, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cording to the Charter of King <hi>John,</hi> which is the famous <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement between the King and his Subjects, after many te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and bloody Contests, wherein the City of <hi>London</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one is comprized by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me, <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Civitas London habeat om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Libertates suas antiquas &amp; consuetudines suas.</hi> The said King <hi>Henry the third</hi> having obtained, as his Father King <hi>John</hi> before him, a Dispensation from the Pope, accounted himself free from his Coronation-Oath, and absolv'd from his frequent solemn Obligations of observing <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> governed tyrannically, having little regard to other Law than his own pleasure and humour, did create such Dissatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46186:10"/> in the People, as at length caused a general Defecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But <hi>Henry</hi> having concluded a firm League with the King of <hi>France,</hi> pawned or mortgaged <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jou</hi> for 300000 li. bought off many of the Malecontents, and with the Assistance of the French and the Popes Thunder, with great difficulty and extream Hazard of his Person (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once both prisoner and sorely wounded) he overcame his Adversaries, and amongst them the Londoners, who had vigorously oppos'd his Arbitrary Proceedings. Those of note, who escaped the Carnage of the great Battle of <hi>Evesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> were outlawed, they, who remtined at home, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned, their Estates confiscated, and says <hi>Mat. Paris, Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem Londinensem privavit suis Privilegiis &amp; Libertatibus:</hi> but <hi>Westmonsteriensis Primores Civitatis poena pecuniaria ad summam non modicam multabantur.</hi> Howsoever, soon after, upon their Submission, he granted unto them divers new Priviledges and Immunities.</p>
            <p>Succeeding Princes were very tender of their Priviledges, as appears by Letter-patents of <hi>Edward the second,</hi> declaring, That whereas the Mayor and good Men of the City, tho not obliged to war out of the City, yet had upon an Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency assisted the King with aid of armed Men, this should not be to the Prejudice of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> City, nor drawn into Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But most eminently in the Charter granted by <hi>Edward the third</hi> in Parliament, wherein was granted and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <q rend="margQuotes">That, whereas in the Great Charter of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> the City of <hi>London</hi> is allowed all their ancient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Customs, and the said Citizens had from the Time of <hi>Edward the Confessor, William the Conqueror</hi> and others our Progenitors, divers Liberties and Customs, as well by the Charter of these our Progenitors, as without Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by ancient Custom, many of which have been in Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits, and by Judgments or Statutes invaded, We will and grant for Us and our Heirs, that they enjoy their Liberties,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46186:11"/> according to the foresaid Great Charter, and all Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto, and Usurpations upon them be revoken and disannull'd.</q> And afterwards in the same same Charter men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions a particular incroachment by our Exchequer Court on the Sheriffs, which he thereby frees them from; as also from unusual Amerciaments in case of Escapes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is also very remarkable, that their being so particularly comprehended in <hi>Magna Charta</hi> did supersede other Statute-Laws, made contradictory to the Liberty and Priviledges of the aforesaid City, as appears at large by the third Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Edward the third.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The said Prince in his fifth Grant declares how sensible he is that his Navy was weakned by the Impoverishing of the City, and Decay of Trade therein; and thereupon grants them further Franchises for the Cities Welfare.</p>
            <p>And because so much depended upon Customs not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in written Records, but only derived by a long <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of Tradition from Times immemorial; and if the City were put upon the Proof, it might create them much Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Expence. <hi>Edward the fourth</hi> granted unto them, that in all Pleas of or upon Customs of the City of <hi>London;</hi> tho the City or Government thereof be a party; The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or and the Aldermen declaring and testifying by their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder, whether there be suc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Custom or not, shall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and Process made accordingly. And in the same Charter it is granted to the Major, Commonalty and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, that tho they, their Predecessors, or Successors have not used, or shall not use, have abused, or shall abuse any of the Priviledges or Customs contained in former Grants, of us or our Progenitors, that yet they shall not incur the Forfeiture of the Premises. This same Prince afterwards, in consideration of many Kindnesses done to him by the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yor and Commonalty of <hi>London,</hi> did grant unto the City divers Offices, specified in his fourth Charter. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46186:11"/> there seemed to be an Emulation or Contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst succeeding Princes, who should most contribute unto its Honour, Wealth and Security. But we shall, to avoid te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diousness, pass over all to the Confirmation of former Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters by King <hi>Iames,</hi> in which the Preface is remarkable, assigning the Reason of former G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nts; <q rend="margQuotes">Whereas many of our Progenitors for free, laudable, multiplyed, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Service done by the Mayor, Commonalty and Citizens of <hi>London,</hi> and their Predecessors, and for divers other ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Causes and Considerations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> We grant a Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all former Charters to the City, and Restauration or Restitution unto all Liberties as fully as ever their Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters enjoyed. And tho they have not used, or have abused a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Authorities, Liberties, Priviledges, Customs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding they may hereafter fully enjoy and use them.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So King <hi>Charles the first:</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Such is our Love to our City of <hi>London,</hi> our Royal Chamber, that whatsoever we shall see necessary or profitable to the Major, Commonalty and Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, we have been and are ready to give unto them; and it pleases Us, that all former Grants be not only confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med but enlarged.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His Majesty now reigning, being sensible how much this City contributed to his Restauration, and how much its good Government, Wealth and Glory would establish his own Power and Dignity, confirmed all preceding Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Words as kind and comprehensive, as can be employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on so solemn an Occasion, which being large and already published, I do thereunto refer the Reader. And from this Epitome of the various Charters and Concessions, together with the Circumstances of Time and Persons, we derive the ensuing Corollaries or Observations, which seem naturally to flow there from.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You may hence learn the great Antiquity of this Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, upon which account with some People it should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more venerable.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:46186:12"/>2. Observe the unanimous Consent of all Princes, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm and enlarge this Charter, apprehending, as is expresly in divers of their Concessions, that they did thereby not only benefit the City, but derive Honour and Advantage upon themselves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That very few of our Kings have attempted to destroy or suspend the Exercise of this Charter, and those who did, laid thereby the Foundation of great Troubles, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways thereupon ensued.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Divers wise Princes, tho highly provok'd, and just Pretences afforded them, for ever to have abolished it, if they had regard only to the Persons, more immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd therein, yet providently discerning the Benefit accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to themselves, and the Nation thereby, did not only confirm but adorn it with new Priviledges.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is hard to conceive how this Charter can be forfeited since it hath not only the Concession of Kings, but the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Parliaments, <hi>That no Part thereof shall be forfeited by Abuse or Disuse:</hi> probably for seeing that some powerful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister or ill-advised Prince might from a Principle of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge or Avarice pretend a Breach of the Charter, and thereupon Forfeiture, and then the Lease must be renewed, or the Tenure voided; whereas nothing is more rational, than that, if any Misdemeanour be committed by any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of a Society, the Criminals only should suffer, and not the rest of the innocent Community; therefore in many of our Charters the Sheriffs, Mayor and other Officers are declared accomptable and punishable for great Offences as other Subjects.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is most apparent that this City was never more peaceable and obsequious, or more contented under the Government of any Prince, from the Time it was erected, than now under that of his present Majesty, whose Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Justice, as it affords us an entire Satisfaction, so no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46186:12"/> in our present Circumstances renders us so uneasy, as the continual Fears, we shall not long enjoy a King so unexceptionably good, who hath reconciled the two seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Extreams of Majesty and Love; exercising with the Wisdom and Authority of a Mighty Prince, the Care and Indulgence of an Affectionate Parent, not only of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, but more especially of this City, which he hath honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, enriched, and secured, by chusing it for the Place of his almost constant Residence.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Dissolution of this Charter will be succeeded with such a train of Mischiefs and Calamities, as the very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection thereon, will possess an honest considerate Man with terror and amazement, one might write a large Volume of the evil Effects and Consequences which would probably ensue, to foresee and enumerate all which, were next to an Impossibility; but so much as is obvious, makes it an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of Confusion, and an Emblem of the last Catastrophe of the Universe, or of the first Chaos: And therefore our most Gracious Prince, is certainly either ignorant of those Proceedings against us, or there is somewhat Mysteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous which we cannot comprehend; but having had such long experience of his Majesty's benign Humour, and certain knowledg of his Propensity to gratify this City in all their reasonable Requests, let us never fear that he will in a moment pluck up by the Root, what was planted and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished by so many of his wise magnanimous Predecessors, and to those, towards whose Prosperity his Majesty himself hath not meanly contributed. Let us therefore trust God and his Vicegerent, and discharging our Duties to both, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all Carking sollicitous Thoughts. But like Innocent Persons, chearfully expect a good Event of this, as of all our other Affairs. Howsoever, I apprehend, it will not be amiss, before I close my Discourse on this Subject, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearse a few of those manifold Inconveniences which will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46186:13"/> necessarily ensue upon the Forfeiture or Abrogation of our Charter, for the instruction of those silly Gulls, who would perswade us voluntarily to abandon all these Franchises, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges, and Emoluments; which by a long Series and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of Services, a great stock of Merit hath been gained. It is some excuse to alleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in order to extenuate our Follies, that we are drunk, therefore in Charity we will suppose these Men drunk with Loyalty; but withal I question not, but before I leave them, to make it evident, that none are or can be good Subjects, till they do own and maintain his Majesty's legal Prerogative as their own Property; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so their Fellow Subjects just Liberties and Privileges, as their own Estates and Lives. But there is amongst us a worse sort of Men, who for base sinister Ends would dissolve the present Constitution of Government, for that none, who know them, will give their Votes towards their obtaining any share in this; they hope, in the new Model, to become con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable, and thereupon censure and declaim against the Present; like the mad Philosopher, who would be buried with his Face downwards, fancying the World would be turned topsy turvy, then all the rest would lie wrong, and he alone right. To inform the former Rank of <hi>Ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muses,</hi> and bring that confusion upon the latter unto which they would reduce us, I shall endeavour to represent the Result of this so much desired and expected Reformation. It is supposed, which yet I can scarcely perswade my self to believe, that some, even among the Governors of our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, are no strangers to, and will not be much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleased with this designed Alteration; let them consider, that the Aldermen, who in the present established Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are very considerable (those above the Chair Justices of course, and of the highest Rank) will be levelled with the meanest Commoner, liable to be Collectors, Pettit-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stables, and other Offices of the lowest Degree; those who
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46186:13"/> expect to be Mayors, deprived of so honourable and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table an Employ; those who have been degraded, as I may say, and on even ground with other Plebeans. A great part of the Revenues of the City forfeit by Statutes of Mortmain, or revert to the Original Donors, their Heirs or Executors. The Commonalty, besides all the Miseries which attend Anarchy, liable to Pressing, to go abroad on War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, from which, by their Charters, they are exempted; not capable, with that ease and advantages of recovering their Debts, exposed to Vexatious Suits, Pleas of the Crown, now being decided in their own Courts, by their own Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers. Aliens will dwell in their City, learn the Mystery of all their Trades, and have equal Advantages with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. No provision for Widows, who abandoned Dower or Jointures, and left to the Custom and Courtesy of the City: Orphans Mony hazardous, if not lost, with not only injury to Citizens, but to many worthy Gentlemen, whose Daughters will be left to great Uncertainties. To say nothing of Freemens Widows and Children, who thereby enjoy great Privileges, to be rescinded. And not to expatiate on their Estates in the Stocks and Treasuries of private Companies, and the Revenues of the said Companies; Revenues and Government of Hospitals. What Confusion and Loss will ensue the intermission of the Offices of Conservators of the River, and Water-balywick; of Packing, Scavage, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, Garbling, Gauging, measuring Coal, Corn, Salt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To pass over Prizage of Wine, Markets, Escheats, Profits, and Emoluments from <hi>Leaden-Hall,</hi> and other publick Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, from weighing, approving, laying, housing divers Commodities; forestalling, ingrossing. But these are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Damages, and are all nothing to what the whole City is at once liable to: We may become a Garison, or rather a Camp; and if we lose the benefit of chusing our Sheriffs, our Lives, Liberties, Estates, lie at the Mercy of such as shall be imposed on us.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:46186:14"/>
            <p>These, and innumerable other Mischiefs we are liable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, if the Charter be rendred invalid; which though we have little cause to fear, during the Administration of our present Sovereign, who hath never hitherto manifested his Power, by embracing Opportunities of oppressing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressing his Subjects: Yet having no possibility of ensuring his Life, who knows what conditioned Princes may succeed him; and we ought, if we can prevent it, to leave nothing to Chance. Let us therefore highly prize our Priviledges, and by all legal Means, maintain that precious Patrimony left us by our Forefathers; behave our selves with all duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful respect to our King, that he may not be induced, by the Importunity of our Enemies, to take every Advantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us. And let us cherish mutual Love among our selves; A Society, no more than a Kingdom, divided, can long subsist. Let every one mind his own Business, and that of the Publick, when legally called thereunto; but let all be transacted without clamour, railing, reviling, with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>desty, meekness, regularly. As I would have none to betray their just Privileges, so neither to claim more than is their Due; for to arrogate more to our selves than is right, is the ready way to lose what we might otherwise justly chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge. I am unwilling, and almost afraid of recapitulating the Inconveniences will by this Resumption redound unto the Supream Magistrate: The old and too too often expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Sentence is, <hi>Necesse est ut multos metuat quem multi timent;</hi> when People are put out of the protection of those Laws they value and like, they are not free or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to give due subjection to those, whereof they do not in their secret thoughts approve, though outward Respects restrain them from declaring it. The next favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Opportunity, or Invitation, whereby they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge their Losses, or recover their Liberties, is usually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced; of which <hi>Richard</hi> the second is an eminent and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:46186:14"/> Instance. When I consider all this, and much more, fit rather for private Thoughts, or communication to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Ministers, than for common Discourse, I am great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly surprized to find what progress is already made in this Affair, and from what Miscarriage, or pretended Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage of the City, it derived its Original. I cannot find any specious colour for this new sort of Inquisition, besides that common Complaint of our Adversaries, That so long as the City chuses Sheriffs, and they assign Juries, the King's most Excellent Majesty, and his most Loyal faithful Subjects, must despair of Justice. Upon which Theme, (good God!) how copious and elegant are they! How clearly and fully do they prove their Charge by induction of Particulars! How many <hi>Ignoramus</hi> Juries! How many honest useful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons brought into trouble, only for their exposing Persons Disaffected, and Actions displeasing to the Government! This, if it be true, all must account a very hainous Crime, and not to be expiated by a less Punishment, than that which they have allotted for it. But if to be accused, would ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any Criminal, how few would be Innocent! We shall therefore impartially examine all their Allegations, and if I do not demonstrate the falseness and futility of them, or at least if I do not, without reserve or disguise, really believe what I declare to others hereof, may I suffer greater Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and worse Punishments, than those I would depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for, and avert from this Renowned City, in which I first drew my Breath: wherein I have led the most comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table part of my Life, and which I hope, dying, to leave to my Posterity, more advanced in Reputation and Prosperity, than when I first entred therein. May it be and continue the deserved Metropolis of so great an Empire, the Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of so good a King; the impregnable Bulwark of the best Religion; the Glory of the most truly generous and easily governable Nation; the worst indeed of Slaves, but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46186:15"/> the best of Subjects; which Character may they deserve and maintain, whilst they are a People, as they have for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 1600 Years already elapsed. <hi>Britanni di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Corn. Taci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>de Vita</hi> Agricolae.</note>
               <hi>Tributa &amp; caetera Imperii munera impigrè obeunt modo injuriae absint, has aegre tolerant; jam domiti ut pareant, nondum ut serviant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having finished what I proposed to represent concerning our Charter, I proceed, according to my promise, more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, to vindicate our Modern Sheriffs and Jurors, whom our Adversaries load with Reproaches, and brand with no less Crimes than Disloyalty and Perjury: From which Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanous Accusations, since we cannot clear our selves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out recriminating, let indifferent Persons judg who have the better Cause and Plea. There is nothing certainly more obvious to all considering People, than that we are beset by a company of Men, who since they dare not attempt the destroying us by Force, do therefore endeavour to compass and effect it by Tricks and Fraud. And it were endless to recount the Ways and Methods which they have been pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing, for the subversion of our Religion, Laws, and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to make us fall a Sacrifice to their Rage, under the charge and imputation of Crimes, whereof their Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences tell them we are altogether Innocent. It were too bold an effort directly to trample upon the English Laws, and therefore they are thinking how to make them as insig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant to the protection of the Guiltless, as if we never had enjoyed any Laws, or were deprived of them by a Right of Conquest. Nor doth any thing occur to their Thoughts, that would be more inservient hereunto, than the obtaining Sheriffs, that they are assured would return such Juries, who would reckon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enough to condemn us of Treason, because we desire to be preserved from coming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Popish Prince;</hi> or because we believe there hath been a Design carried on by those of the Romish Faction, for the
<pb facs="tcp:46186:15"/> Destruction of the King, the Subversion of the established Government. And after all the Clamour that hath been raised against the late Sheriffs, and those Juries which they have returned to serve either in Capital or Civil Causes; We defie the utmost of the Malice of our Enemies, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance one just Exception against the Righteousness and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiality of their several and respective Verdicts. Alas what kind of Juries are those returned in the Neighbouring Counties, at which nevertheless no Offence is taken, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parison of those, that have been from time to time upon the Pannels in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middlesex!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us but ballance the Acquitment of <hi>Gascoign</hi> and <hi>Wake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> with the <hi>Ignoramus</hi>'s returned either at the Best a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Colledg,</hi> or that against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very sober Man must acknowledg, that if it be lawful to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign a Jury, there is more to be objected to the disparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of those, than there is to asperse these.</p>
            <p>Nor can there be a greater Evidence of the Integrity and Justice of the late Juries, than that they have carried it equally towards all sorts of Persons: for did not the Jury in March 1681 bring in an <hi>Ignoramus</hi> upon a Bill exhibited against diverse Persons, under a pretence of Recusancy; and this, not because they favoured them or the Popish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but because the Evidence was not full, or the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses such, as a wise and honest Man ought to believe?</p>
            <p>And is it not strange, that the Jury which rejected the Bill against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury,</hi> should be so severely blamed, when it is so well known, that the principal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons then in Commission on the Bench have often said, that they must have done as the Jury did, had it been their Lot to have been in their Place?</p>
            <p>Can any Thing tend more to the Vindication of the late Juries, than that they have never failed to give Verdicts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst these of their own Principles, and their best Friends,
<pb facs="tcp:46186:16"/> if the Evidence before them appeared any ways clear and full, and that the Witnesses were such, as that credit could be given to them; Witness the Case some time ago against <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> and that of late against Mr. <hi>Best.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are any so unreasonable as to expect, that a Jury should find Bills upon the Depositions of such as themselves know to be perjured and infamous Rascals? and of this complexion and stamp were most of those that swore against the Earl of <hi>Shaftsbury:</hi> Or would they have a Jury convict a Person, upon the Testimony of a Woman, that would not declare and express her self in the very Court, but as she was prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted, nor without asking her Suborner what she should say next, as in the case of <hi>Sam. Harris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, What Jurors did ever better merit the Character of good and legal Men, than those, whereof our Grand Juries have been mostly composed? Men of good Fame, free from all reasonable Suspicion of any Design for themselves or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, upon the Estates or Lives of any suspected Criminals, or had any Quarrel or Controversy with any of them; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, impartial, of sufficient Understanding and Estate. Let us compare their Verdicts with those, of any which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded them in <hi>London</hi> in our Memory, and I perswade my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, they will not be disgraced by the parallel. Nor shall we decline to challenge the adjacent Counties, whether they can produce Verdicts founded on more Reason, or where the Jurors acted with more deliberation and indifferency: I am ashamed to nominate them in the same breath with our sprightly inspired Association-abhorring Jurors; who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn Persons on Reputation of I know not whom; whereas it is customary with ours to refuse Bills from other Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, unless they reexamin the Evidence; These, tho absent, with a breath condemn, whom the most judicious Jury ever sate in <hi>London,</hi> upon fair and strict Inquiry, acquitted; to the full Satisfaction of hundreds of honourable Persons there present.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46186:16"/>
            <p>I intended to have enumerated all the remarkable Verdicts given within these two Years last past, whereof I have a most particular Account, with the Reasons and Motives inducing them; but I being prolix, and what I have already specified, being, in my Opinion, their sufficient Apology, I shall su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persede that Task, and conclude, after I have remembred you how great a Trust and Power is lodged in Juries; so that as a Modern Judicious Author, wisely observes, <hi>That 'tis the greatest in the Nation, next to the Legislative; the Concernments of all Commoners; the Honour, Reputation, Estates, and Lives of the Nobility is submitted to their Censure: Their Duty is to Indict Offend rs, and protect the Innocent in their Reputations, Lives, and Interests, from false Accusers, and malicious Conspirators.</hi> Of how great Consequence is it then unto us all, to have good Juries? How carefully ought we to provide for the Security of our Lives, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> against such as would destroy us by false Accusation and Perjury? And except our Sheriffs be wise, careful, and integruous, we may prognosticate great Hazards to divers Persons, whom we cannot but believe in our Consciences to be innocent of those Crimes whereof their Adversaries would soon charge them, could they obtain Juries like to prove so severe, as those were lately to <hi>Wilmore</hi> and Sheriff <hi>Pilkington.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, my dear fellow-Citizens, what remains, but that I should exhort you strenuously to assert and maintain your undoubted right of chusing She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffs. Be not afrighted by Menaces, or wheedled by Promises of an Equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, to part with so essential and necessary a Branch of your Charter; which should you neglect or resign, (pardon the harshness of the Expression) you will thereby become Traitors to the Community, and Violaters of that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Trust which you are obliged by your Interest, and engaged by your Oaths, faithfully &amp; fearlesly to discharge. Nay, tho Persons of the greatest Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority amongst you should interpose, let not that influence you to abandon your Unvaluable Privileges, and complement you selves into Misery; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly they who, by misrepresentation, have raised such jealousy and distrust of you, will, when they have obtained, by this Incroachment, an almost De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spotick Power, exercise it in a manner will not be very agreeable, and afford you sufficient cause bitterly to lament your unaccountable, your unexcusable Credulity and Folly, and will render you mean in the Eyes of them you have gratified, hateful and abhorred to those you betray. As for what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards your Duty and Love to your Prince, these will be more signalized by your putting a value upon his Gifts, than by your slighting and rejecting them. And indeed we cannot reasonably believe or imagine his Majesty will require our subjecting our selves; and all we have, unto his Absolute Will and Pleasure, he having ever hitherto preferred an upright equal Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before an unlimited Domination; and that humane benign temper, wherein he excels all Men, will certainly dispose him to pardon us if we cannot, dare not repose that confidence in his Ministers we could in himself. The best and wisest of Princes, see most Transactions with other Mens Eyes,
<pb facs="tcp:46186:17"/> hear with their Ears, and Act by their Hands; the concealing Addition, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a Word in Speech, or Circumstance in Actions, we may daily ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, renders Cases very different from what they were really: Therefore having so many, and such powerful Enemies, as I have before demonstrated, our only Security is, the established Law, by which we are governed; and we have his Majesty's Royal Word, that shall be the Rule of all his Actions, and equally distributed to all his Subjects. Whilst the Laws have free course, and are uncontrouled by Justiciaries, duly interpreted, faithfully represen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that Sheriffs take care to return equal Juries, no Innocent need fear. Our Adversaries may accuse us, brand us with odious Names and Characters, or at worst, imprison us; but the Law, which is impartial, cannot be brib'd or biass'd, and our honest Neighbours will soon relieve us. Nay, let the whole Fraternity of tutor'd Witnesses appear against the meanest Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, whose Cause is just, I question not, but our discerning Juries will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily detect the Fraud, and acquit the Oppressed. Birds that have once escaped the Snare, are not easily entangled again. The same Cheat, in the same Age, must not be brought often upon the Stage; or if it be again represented, what Impunity its Actors promise themselves, or what Encouragement and Assurances they may receive from others, I know not; but unless we are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digiously blind and infatuated, they cannot, methinks, reasonably hope for success. Let us then cheerfully unite in this laudable Resolution, to chuse such Magistrates for the Year ensuing, as are endued with Wisdom and Courage, who have obtained a good Report for their Dutifulness to their Sovereign, and Love to their Fellow-Citizens; who are uncapable of being by either Side biassed and corrupted; Men actively prudent, honestly zealous, of brave, firm, manly Resolutions; who will not be afraid to discharge their Duty in in the fullest and utmost extent. If Almighty God hath designed our Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness, he will provide Persons thus qualified, and inspire and animate us to elect them. And such Ministers will be not only a great Security to the City, in this time of great Fear and extremest Exigence, but doutbless very acceptable to his Majesty, whose most admirable Humanity, and tender Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to his People, will certainly dispose him to pity a distracted City, upon the brink of Ruine, by reason of Jealousies and Divisions; and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at our Choice of vertuous, peaceable, discreet Sheriffs, who may greatly contribute to the accommodating our Differences, removing our mutual Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices and Mistakes; whereby this City will be rendred more capable of serving his Majesty, and relishing the Blessings of his mild benign Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; a commendable Emulation will be excited, who shall manifest most dutiful Respect unto his Royal Person, and most liberally contribute to the Support of his Government: And being delivered from the fear of our Enemies, we shall join in celebrating his Praises, continually supplicating him b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom Kings rule, to grant him uninterrupted Health, long L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe, a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and prosperous Reign; and that whosoever su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceeds him may imitate and <hi>express</hi> all his Princely Vertues, whereto let every Loyal Subject say, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:46186:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>